Alexander A. Liveright Papers
Alexander A. Liveright Papers
1934-1969
1956-1969
Liveright, A. A. (Alexander Albert), 1907-1969
8.5 linear ft.
Alexander A. Liveright was a professor of adult education and director of the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) for more than ten years. Correspondence, minutes and reports which highlight Liveright’s professional interests and affiliations. Included are papers generated while professor in the schools of education at Boston University and Syracuse University, as director of The Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, and as founding member and Secretary of the International Congress of University Adult Education. Sagamore Conference papers and those of the New Institutional Forms Project, a research project begun by Liveright to study the development of comprehensive adult education programs, also appear in the collection. International adult education is the focus of records from trips to Australia, Hong Kong, India, New Zealand, the Philippines, and Thailand. Miscellaneous material includes newspaper clippings, War Manpower Commission documents, and material from the Highlander Folk School.
149138
Biographical History
Alexander A. Liveright was born in Philadelphia, PA, in 1907. He received his bachelor's degree from the University of Wisconsin (1929), an M.A. in Guidance and Counseling from Teachers College, Columbia University (1930), and a Ph.D. in Adult Education from the University of Chicago (1956). Over his thirty-year career he was a professor, consultant, researcher and director for various institutions and universities specializing in adult and continuing education.
Liveright was director of the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) from 1956 until its dissolution in 1968. (The Center was independently located in Chicago from 1951 until 1965, and then was affiliated with Boston University.) In 1966 he spent four months on a round-the-world study sponsored by the Carnegie Corporation. As director of CSLEA, and in his own right, he was involved in a wide range of adult and continuing education programs in the United States, had many contacts with adult education in other countries, and was a leader in international activities such as the International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE), of which he was a founding member and, at the time of his death, secretary.
He was on the faculty of George Williams College, Columbia College, University College of the University of Chicago, and the University of Michigan; a member of the Visiting Committee for Summer Schools and Extension Division of Harvard; Executive Director, American Council on Race relations; Director of Labor Education, University of Chicago; consultant to the Research Bureau, U.S. Office of Education; consultant to the Academy for Educational Development; consultant to the Air Line Pilots Association; consultant to the Montana Farmers Union; and Conference Coordinator for the 1956 AEA Conference. From 1967 until his death in 1969, Liveright was Associate Professor of Adult Education at Syracuse University.
Dr. Liveright authored numerous articles, monographs, and book chapters and served on the editorial boards of Convergence and Adult Education.
He died in 1969.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Papers reflecting Liveright's activity in both the CSLEA and ICUAE, as well as his wide-ranging national and international involvement in adult education, form the bulk of the Alexander A. Liveright Papers. Notable in this portion of the collection are papers from the Sagamore Conference (September, 1960) marking the inception of the ICUAE. The CSLEA (with Liveright as its Director) was one of six adult education organizations sponsoring the Conference; Liveright became Secretary of the ICUAE.
Subjects covered include travels associated with the First World Conference and European Study Tour, adult education in Africa, Latin America, and Australia, as well as UNESCO meetings and conferences. The folders pertaining to the CSLEA International Comparative Education Conference at Exeter, New Hampshire are of note, since they form the basis of The Exeter Papers, published by Liveright (1966).
The bulk of the remainder of the collection is from the years 1968-1969, incorporating the phase-out of the CSLEA, Liveright's move to Syracuse University, and his ensuing illness. At Syracuse University, Liveright became associated with the ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education, plus numerous research and publication projects (Liveright had hoped to complete a book on leaders in adult education before he died). During his illness and at the time of his death, some of Liveright's administrative duties were shared by James Whipple and Robert Blakely; in addition, John Ohliger, Robert Theobald and David Mosconi completed publication projects in progress.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into series based on the various organizations and projects: Boston University, CSLEA, ICUAE, the New Institutional Forms Project, and Syracuse University. Travel includes material relating to trips to Australia, Hong Kong, India, New Zealand, Thailand and the Philippines. A final division covers Other activities while Miscellaneous includes photographs, clippings, and two audio tapes by Dr. Manet Fowler. The tapes record her interview with C. B. Ratchford, and refer to Liveright in two brief interchanges on Tape 1: on Side A of (after about 5 mm of tape), and on Side B (after about 10 mm of tape).
Because the collection was received as two separate donations several years apart and the two sections were processed separately, the intellectual order of contents shown in the finding aid is not necessarily the same as the physical order. For example, the CSLEA material is located in boxes 1, 2 and 8. Refer to the box numbers given in the finding aid for the correct location of a particular item.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing.
The following are particularly closely related to the Alexander A. Liveright Papers:
Organizations:
Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC) Records
Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) Records
Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE) Records
Fund for Adult Education (FAE) Records
Galaxy Conference
International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE) Records
National University Extension Association (NUEA) Records
Syracuse University Publications in Continuing Education (SUPCE) Records
University Council on Education for Public Responsibility (UCEPR) Records
Individuals
Robert J. Blakely Papers
Alexander N. Charters Papers
Paul Sheats Papers
James B. Whipple Papers
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Blakely, Robert J.; Charters, Alexander N.; Liveright, A. A. (Alexander Albert), 1907-; Sheats, Paul H., 1907-; Whipple, James B.; Boston University, School of Education.; Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults.; ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education; Highlander Folk School (Monteagle, Tenn.); International Conference on University Adult Education (1960: Sagamore, N.Y.); International Congress of University Adult Education.; New Institutional Forms Project.; Syracuse University. -- School of Education.; Syracuse University. -- ERIC Clearinghouse on Adult Education.; United States -- War Manpower Commission.; University Council on Education for Public Responsibility.; Adult education.; Continuing education -- United States.; Continuing education -- Study and teaching.; Educators, United States; Correspondence.; Invoices.; Speeches (documents); Curricula.; Interviews.; Proposals.; Reports.; Minutes (administrative records); Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Boston University
  - Problems in Adult Education, 1965-1968 (Box 1)
  - Problems in Adult Education, 1965-1968; course outlines and student papers; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Seminar in Comparative and International Adult Education, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Seminar on Comparative Adult Education, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Student papers, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
- Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA)
  - 4th Leadership Conference for University Adult Education, 1956 (Box 8)
  - Academy study, undated; draft of chapters 3, 4 and 5, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Anglo-American Conference, 1963-1965 (Box 8)
  - Board meetings, minutes
    - 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - 1957 (Box 2)
  - Board minutes, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Conference on Comparative Adult Education/Exeter, New Hampshire
    - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 8)
    - Reports & info., 1966 (Box 8)
    - Roster, 1966 (Box 8)
    - Discussion papers, 1966 (Box 8)
    - Working papers, 1966
      - Canada (English) (Box 8)
      - Canada (French) (Box 8)
      - Denmark (Box 8)
      - France (Box 8)
      - Hong Kong (Box 8)
      - India (Box 8)
      - Puerto Rico (Box 8)
      - Sudan (Box 8)
      - USA (Box 8)
      - Yugoslavia (Box 8)
  - Core programs, 1960-1961 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - Australia, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Hawaii, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - India, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Israel, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Malaysia and Singapore, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Nepal, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - New Zealand, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - Philippines, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Thailand, 1967 (Box 2)
  - CSLEA phase-out
    - James Whipple, 1968-1969 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 8)
    - Syracuse University, 1968 (Box 8)
  - Foundations
    - Carnegie Corp., 1964-1969 (Box 8)
    - Ford Foundation, 1959-1968 (Box 8)
    - Standard Oil of New Jersey, 1966-1967 (Box 8)
    - United States Steel, 1964-1967 (Box 8)
    - Western Electric, 1965-1969 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1964-1965 (Box 8)
  - Grants and submissions, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Impact study and supplement, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Program goals study, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
  - Proposals
    See also Syracuse University: Kellogg Foundation proposal
    - Audience Education proposal, undated (Box 8)
    - Correspondence Ed. Research Proj., 1964-1965 (Box 8)
    - Directory for Independent Study, 1964-1968 (Box 8)
    - Research & Development Center, 1966 (Box 8)
  - State University of New York (SUNY) /Albany, 1964-1968 (Box 8)
  - University Council on Education for Public Responsibility (UCEPR), 1967-1968 (Box 8)
  - U.S. Dept. of Health, Ed., Welfare (DHEW)/Office of Education (USOE)
    - Bureau of Research, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box 8)
    - Follow-up, 1966-1968 (Box 8)
    - Research & Development Center, 1966-1967 (Box 8)
  - Visitors
    - Drew, Vernon, 1964-1968 (Box 8)
    - Kelly, Tom, 1967-1968 (Box 8)
    - Samolovcev, Borivoj, 1964-1969 (Box 8)
    - Singh, Amrik, 1967-1968 (Box 8)
    - Stretton, Dulcie, 1967-1968 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1962-1968 (Box 8)
- ICUAE
  - Business
    - Correspondence
      - Crowley, Desmond, 1965-1969 (Box 8)
      - Dakin, James, 1965-1969 (Box 8)
      - Friesen, John, 1965-1969 (Box 8)
      - Howard, Campbell, 1966-1969 (Box 8)
      - Hughes, Ieuan, 1967-1968 (Box 8)
      - Jessup, Frank, 1966-1969 (Box 8)
      - Kidd, James Roby, 1964-1969
        - Convergence, 1968-1969 (Box 8)
      - Melling, John, 1965-1967 (Box 8)
      - Okamura, Seiichi, 1965-1968 (Box 8)
      - Canadian Assoc. Adult Ed. (CAE), 1966-1967 (Box 8)
      - Canadian Assoc. Depts. of Ext. & Summer Schools, CADESS, 1966-1967 (Box 8)
      - India-Rajasthan, 1965-1969 (Box 8)
      - Uganda-Makerere Univ. College, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
    - Executive Committee, Members (alphabetical)
      - Borinski, Fritz, 1965-1969; correspondence (Box 9)
      - Coles, E.K. Townsend, 1963-1969; correspondence (Box 9)
      - al-Halim, Amad Abd, 1966-1967 (Box 9)
      - Lai, T.C., 1964-1969 (Box 9)
      - McCallion, W.J. (chair), 1963-1968 (Box 9)
      - Raybould, Sidney, 1965-1969 (Box 9)
      - Savicevic, Dusan, 1966-1969 (Box 9)
      - Schwartz, Bertrand, 1966-1968 (Box 9)
    - Executive Committee
      - Minutes, 1960-1963 (Box 9)
      - Minutes, correspondence, Jul-Nov 1965 (Box 9)
      - Minutes, agenda, corres., Boston-Buffalo, 1966 (Box 9)
      - Minutes, correspondence, Syracuse-NYC, 1967
        - Education Permanente Seminar, 1967; speeches (Box 9)
        - Education Permanente Seminar, 1967; corres. & speeches (Box 9)
      - Minutes, correspondence, Leeds-Syracuse, 1968 (Box 9)
    - Legal affairs
      - Geo. Overton, 1962-1967 (Box 9)
      - Legal/financial affairs, 1964-1968 (Box 9)
      - UNESCO affiliation, 1962-1963 (Box 9)
    - Membership affairs
      - Ballots, institutional & individual, undated (Box 9)
      - Correspondence & misc., 1963-1966 (Box 9)
      - Dues, 1963-1968 (Box 9)
      - Dues, 1967-1968 (Box 9)
      - Information, 1965-1968 (Box 9)
      - Invoices, individual memberships, 1967-1970 (Box 9)
      - Invoices, institutional memberships, 1967-1969 (Box 9)
      - Lifetime membership, Seiichi Okamura, 1966 (Box 9)
      - List - individual, 1966 (Box 9)
      - List - institutional, 1966 (Box 9)
      - Prospective members, 1966-1967 (Box 9)
    - Publications
      - Newsletter
        - First issue, 1961 (Box 9)
        - Mailing list, 1965 (Box 9)
        - Subscriptions, 1965-1967 (Box 9)
        - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 9)
        - Diana Ironside, newsletter & personal correspondence, 1965-1969 (Box 9)
      - Adult Ed publications, 1966-1968 (Box 9)
      - ICUAE Adult Ed. Directory, [1966?] (Box 9)
  - Conferences
    - Africa
      - Cables, 1961 (Box 9)
      - Correspondence, 1961-1962 (Box 9)
      - Visa information, 1961 (Box 10)
      - African Adult Education Institute, 1961-1964 (Box 10)
      - Ghana
        - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 10)
        - Memoranda & miscellaneous, 1961-1962 (Box 10)
        - Reports, 1961-1962 (Box 10)
      - Basutoland, 1962 (Box 10)
      - African Trip, follow-up, 1962-1963 (Box 10)
      - Africa, correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 10)
    - Australia
      - Conference, 1961-1964 (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous, 1963 (Box 10)
    - Europe
      - Study tour, 1963-1965 (Box 10)
      - Study tour, memos, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
      - Study tour, questionnaires, 1964 (Box 10)
      - Study tour, participants, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
      - Study tour, cancellations, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
      - Study tour, arrangements, 1965 (Box 10)
      - Study tour-Oxford, 1965
        - Britain, correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box 10)
      - Study tour-UNESCO, 1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, Krogerup Denmark, correspondence, 1963-1964 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, 1963-1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, business, 1963-1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, Ford Grant, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, correspondence/papers, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, ICCE/correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, Secretary's report, 1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, executive minutes, 1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, resolution (Box 10)
      - World Conference, memoranda, 1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, participants, 1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, newsletter, 1965 (Box 10)
      - World Conference, newsletter/correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 10)
    - Latin America
      - Correspondence, 1961-1963 (Box 10)
      - Memoranda, 1961-1963 (Box 10)
      - Correspondence & lists, 1962 (Box 10)
      - Latin America/S. American conference, 1962 (Box 10)
      - Latin America, 1963; correspondence (Box 10)
      - Inter-American Conference, 1964 (Box 10)
      - Inter-American Conference, 1964-1968; correspondence (Box 10)
    - United States
      - Sagamore Conference
        - Agenda, minutes, participants, 1960-1961 (Box 11)
        - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 11)
        - Speeches, Sep 1960 (Box 11)
      - Other conference notifications, 1964-1968 (Box 11)
      - Other conferences, information/reports, 1964-1968 (Box 11)
    - UNESCO, research & training grant, 1967-1968 (Box 11)
    - UNESCO conferences, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
    - 2nd World Conference, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
- New Institutional Forms Project
  - Consultant panel, 1969
    - Project #1 (Box 2)
    - Project #2 (Box 3)
  - Contract and proposal, 1968 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, Ivan Lappin, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - Draft Proposals
    - Comments, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1966-1968; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - National Focus Activity, 1969 (Box 3)
  - National forms, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Panel meetings, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Program budget, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Proposal and background material, 1966-1969 (Box 4)
  - Report, inquiries re, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Reports to Committee of Adult Education Organizations (CAEO), 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Staff appointments, 1969; correspondence (Box 4)
  - Survey form, city of Syracuse, 1969 (Box 4)
- Syracuse University
  - Academy for Education Development, 1967-1969 (Box 11)
  - Academy for Education Development, report (Box 11)
  - Academy for Education Development - Dave Mosconi, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
  - Adult education
    - Course outline and student papers, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Programs, 1967-1969 (Box 5)
    - Related programs, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Appointment to staff, 1968-1969; correspondence (Box 5)
  - Continuing education, 1969; publications list (Box 5)
  - Continuing education publications, 1968; correspondence (Box 5)
  - Faculty interviews, drafts, ca.1968 (Box 5)
  - Highlander Research and Education Center, 1969 (Box 5)
  - International Seminar on Adult Education, 1969 (Box 5)
  - International Seminar/Galaxy Conference, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
  - Kellogg Foundation proposal, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
  - National Institute for Independent Study, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
  - New Institutional Forms, 1969 (Box 11)
  - Miller, Paul A., 1968-1969 (Box 11)
  - Publication Activity
    - Adult Education Information, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
    - Continuing Education for Adults, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
    - ERIC Advisory Committee, 1968; 1966-1969 (Box 11)
    - ERIC, 1968-1969; correspondence (Box 11)
    - Kapoor, Sudarshan, correspondence (Box 11)
    - Liveright, Alexander, 1969 (Box 11)
    - Ohliger, John, 1969 (Box 11)
  - UNESCO, Ruth Lazarus, 1968-1969 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Archives, 1968-1969 (Box 12)
    - Planning schedule, 1968 (Box 12)
    - School of Ed/Ph.D. Orals, 1968 (Box 12)
    - Recruitment, etc., 1968-1969 (Box 12)
    - Alex Charters, memos, undated (Box 12)
- Travel
  - Australia, Canberra, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Australia, Melbourne, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Australia, New South Wales, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
  - Australia, Perth, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Australia, University of Sydney, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Australia, Tasmania, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Hong Kong (Box 5)
  - India (general), 1967 (Box 5)
  - India, University of Rajasthan, 1967 (Box 5)
  - New Zealand, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Philippines, 1967 (Box 6)
  - Thailand, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
- Other Activities
  - American Association of Jr. Colleges, 1964-1969 (Box 12)
  - American Council on Education, 1968-1969 (Box 12)
  - American Education Association (AEA)
    - Professional Standards Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 12)
    - Continuing education, 1967-1968 (Box 12)
    - Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE), 1967-1969 (Box 12)
      - Reports, 1967-1969 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 12)
  - Cleveland State University, 1966-1969 (Box 12)
  - College Entrance Examination Board (CEEB)
    - General, 1966-1969 (Box 12)
    - Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 12)
    - Directory, 1966-1969 (Box 12)
  - Delbert Clark Award, 1968-1969 (Box 12)
  - General Electric Seminar, 1968 (Box 12)
  - Harvard College, Board of Overseers
    - Correspondence, 1965-1969 (Box 12)
    - Reginald Phelps, 1968-1969 (Box 12)
  - Highlander Folk School
    - 1957-1962 (Box 12)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 12)
  - Leaders in Adult Education, [1968]-1969 (Box 12)
  - National Adult Education Resources Institute, 1967; confidential memoranda (Box 6)
  - National Educational TV, 1964-1968 (Box 12)
  - Ontario Institute for Studies in Education, 1968 (Box 12)
  - South-East Asian Institute of Adult Education, 1966-1968 (Box 7)
  - Theobald, Robert, 1966-1969; book contract & correspondence (Box 12)
  - US Office of Education (USOE)/Region 2, 1968-1969 (Box 12)
  - University of Pittsburgh, Board of Visitors, 1968-1969 (Box 12)
  - War Manpower Commission
    - War Manpower Commission, 1942 (Box 6)
    - Confidential study for, 1942 (Box 7)
    - Office of Emergency Management, War Manpower Commission, 1943 (Box 7)
    - U.S.A. Before War Manpower Commission, 1943 (Box 7)
  - WCOTP, mailing list, undated (Box 12)
- Miscellaneous
  - Audio tapes - interview of C.B. Ratchford by Dr. Manet Fowler, undated (Box 12)
  - Clippings
    - Newspaper clippings, 1934-1935 (Box 6)
    - Printed papers and newspaper clippings, 1968-1969 (Box 7)
  - Collected papers, 1966-1968 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1963-1967 (Box 6)
    - Blakely, Robert, 1965-1969 (Box 12)
    - Daigneualt, George, 1968 (Box 12)
    - Houle, Cyril, 1968-1969 (Box 12)
    - Other correspondence, 1962-1969 (Box 12)
    - Illness, 1969 (Box 12)
  - Dissertation proposals, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Notes on various topics, 1966-1968 (Box 7)
  - Photographs
    - Alexander A. Liveright, undated (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous photos, 1951-[n.d.] (Box 12)